[Music]
welcome back to the next
episode of our chocolate series today is
a nice simple one we're not going to do
any comparisons or anything what we're
going to do is we're going to make a
valrona cocoa base no added chocolate
we're going to up the dextrose a little
bit
drop the sucrose or normal table sugar
down a bit
and just see what the result is see how
this compares to some of the others so
as normal the recipe is down in the
description
and we're on this journey to try and
find what obviously it's selective
because it's me making it and it's my
opinion
what i consider the best chocolate ice
cream this is gonna probably be a fairly
long journey
we've compared some cocoa powders we've
looked at some of the other ingredients
we've talked about how
the addition of physical chocolate in
your recipes can affect your ice cream
and
i recently bought the guitars
cooker rouge
that actually makes a really nice
chocolate ice cream it's not quite as
strong as valrona
but
it's got a really it gives you that same
kind of chewy fudginess to it it's got a
really nice smooth taste so i may well
use that again
in the near future we might have to do
you know like a showdown towards the end
of this series but um
let's just get stuck in and make this
one you know how this goes by now you
put all your ingredients in the pan
especially with cocoa just dissolve the
sugars
warm your base up add your cocoa powder
in and let it bloom for you know five or
six minutes now in this recipe i've
added one thing and that is a commercial
grade stabilizer which has
emulsifiers in it that's to aid
the emulsion of the base that's to try
and get the fats of the cocoa powder
dissipated nicely
if you don't have that you can use egg
yolks if you wish but
otherwise when your base is warmed up to
temperature take it off the hob put it
in a container add your cream and then
put it back in the fridge again as
normal it needs to cool right down to
the temperature of your fridge it's
gonna take at least four hours once
that's ready
take it out the fridge give it a nice
mix make sure that it's all well
incorporated again and put it in your
machine to churn
as there's no add-ins or any fancy
ingredients here just load your tub up
and then put it in a freezer for a few
hours
if you really want to do some add-ins
with what was left in this churn i put
in some hard fudge and then a liquid
chocolate fudge as well just to see how
that turned out you know what why not
chocolate double fudge thank you very
much
[Music]
no fancy tubs
my wife's out with
our daughter for the day
but
this is just plain chocolate ice cream
so i don't know what she'd do a tub for
this anyway
let's get some dished up and see how
this one turns out
[Music]
so
valrona it's very dark
cocoa powder
it's uh i'll tell you what
i mean it's so dark you can
barely see it in there
it's a really rich strong
almost overpowering
chocolate smell to it but
you know it's one of the biggest
well-known brands
for chocolate products out there
loads of professional chefs bakers etc
all use
of our owner i mean and guitars as well
but to be fair is there that much of a
difference that you can tell between a
cheap cocoa powder that occur cocoa
powder that we use that we've used
before our link to the video where we
went through that
makes a really good chocolate ice cream
it's not expensive you can't buy it
everywhere you have to buy it from a
supplier but
i think that one kilo bag worked out
something like six pounds
for me which is what i don't know
eight dollars something like that
so let's see what the result is here
fudgy straight away i can tell just by
putting a spoon through it
[Music]
valrona does something special i don't
know why because when you look at the
ingredients
it's cocoa powder acidity regulators
potassium carbonate it's got to be the
combination or or one of those second
two that
that makes
such a nice chocolate ice cream
it's an absolute shame it's
if not the most one of the most
expensive cocoa powders on the market
now considering this is probably two or
three or four times the price
of any of the other ones we've looked at
in this series do i think it's worth it
i do
i do think it's worth it
is it worth the addition to guitars
guitars is probably
25 cheaper than this
now there's a competition there's a
balance let me get that
cocoa powder
it's remembering to use one of these
things you know when you've got a young
god these things i keep forgetting and
then you can't get into the cupboards
and anyway here we go
guitars
this is
this is this is a fight right
here their
guitar powder is lighter in color
than verona
they both produced a fudgy finish
they both have a very strong flavor of
chocolate color-wise this comes out just
a little different to this
it's a little redder
you know the recipe is is great
if you follow the channel a while you
see that i use dextrose a fair bit in
the recipes dextrose you know without
going too much into it it changes the
freezing point of your ice cream so it
doesn't have the sweetness of table
sugar but actually affects the freezing
point more so if you substitute 50 of
your sugar with dextrose what you'll
actually get is a softer ice cream that
doesn't taste as sweet but does
allow you to create a recipe that suits
you
some people's freezers
you know they're
minus 25
c
and if you make any ice cream it's just
it's just going to go rock solid in
there so you can start looking at
adjusting your sugars your dextrose you
get that with invert sugars as well but
you can adjust the different types of
sugar to help with your recipe like me i
like my ice creams to be scoopable
straight out of the freezer which is why
i make them with the sugars and con
sugar contents i do so i don't have to
sit there for five ten fifteen minutes
harkendale's looking at you
to be able to get it out the tub i mean
gone are the days where i used to take
the tub open up and start eating now
i've got to open it up and leave it
there and look at it drooling
and everyone else around me looking at
it it's before you know it's a fight
like the zombie apocalypse and we're all
throwing spoons and ice cream at each
other i just want to take it out freezer
and eat it so chocolate ice cream has a
has a habit of going quite hard because
people don't account for the solids and
the additional fats in the cocoa powder
those two things alone can make your ice
cream go really hard so you need to
start thinking about how to reduce that
effect in your chocolate ice cream
what i think we'll do next is probably
do a direct comparison of these two
will take
a recipe maybe even just this recipe
and we'll make identical ice creams just
substitute the two cocoa powders direct
comparison
and see where we go
i can't keep buying every cocoa powder
out there because there are thousands
and thousands of different ones
but
if you've got a specific cocoa powder in
mind that you'd like me to have a look
at let me know you can find us on
facebook you can find us on instagram
obviously check out the comments down in
this video as well let me know if
there's something you want me to look at
if i can buy it i'll try and have a look
as long as it's not going to cost the
earth i don't make any money from doing
these youtube videos
so
there we go another episode in search of
the best chocolate ice cream
is my favorite flavor
vanilla just doesn't cut it for me it's
i find it quite boring but i know there
are lots of people out there that find
chocolate ice cream quite boring so each
our own
anyway i hope you enjoyed this
ramble on chocolate ice cream and you'll
join me next time when we'll do a direct
comparison of these two and try and
eliminate one of them try and go further
up the ladder in the hunt for the best
chocolate ice cream out there anyway
don't forget to like and subscribe and
we'll see you next week
[Music]
you